<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The kingdoms divisions anatomized, together with a vindication of the Armies proceedings. By Franciscus Leinsula.</title>
            <author>Lisle, Francis.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88310</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2369</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E545_25</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206071</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865259</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865259</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117498</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88310)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117498)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 84:E545[25])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The kingdoms divisions anatomized, together with a vindication of the Armies proceedings. By Franciscus Leinsula.</title>
                  <author>Lisle, Francis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Clowes, for Hannah Allen, at the Crown in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Franciscus Leinsula = Francis Lisle.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March. 1st 1648".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117498:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE KINGDOMS DIVISIONS <hi>ANATOMJZED,</hi> Together with a
VINDICATION OF THE ARMIES PROCEEDINGS.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Franciſcus Leinſula.</hi>
            </p>
            <q> 
               <p>Shall there be evill in a City, and the Lord hath not done
it.</p>
               <bibl>Amos. 3.6.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q> 
               <p>Heare O our God, for we are deſpiſed, and turn their Reproach
upon their own head: They which builded on the wall, and they that hear
burdens; every one, with one of his hands wrought in the work, And with the
other hand held a weapon; for the builders every one, had his ſword guirded
by his ſide, &amp;c.</p>
               <bibl>Nehe. 4.4.17.18.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>John Clowes,</hi> for <hi>Hannah
Allen,</hi> at the Crown in <hi>Popes-head Alley.</hi> 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:117498:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, <hi>John Bradſhaw,</hi> Lord
Preſident of the High Court of Juſtice.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving heard an Honourable Report of you, bearing an Honourable
Reſpect to you, And decerning your readines to imbrace and accept, and not
ſlight; or much leſſe deſpiſe the day of ſmall things, <hi>Zach.
4.10.</hi> hath moved me though unworthy to aſſume the boldneſſe to
preſent your Honour with theſe few and rude lines; eſpecially,
conſidering your Honours readineſſe, with others of Gods Worthies in
Parliament, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and high Court of Juſtice, to proſecute Gods work; And
that with a ſpirit of freedom and courage, notwithſtanding the multitude of
<hi>Renums</hi> and <hi>Shiniſhais, Tatnais,</hi> and <hi>Shether-boznais,
Sanballats,</hi> and <hi>Tobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs,</hi> with their Companions, who face in
oppoſition, <hi>Ezra 4.9. 5.3. Neh. 4.1.3.</hi> and truly, my Lord, but face;
for I really believe, if of themſelves, they make not an honourable Retreat,
they will firſt or laſt be driven back with ſhame and diſgrace; Let the
haters of the Lord flie before him, And let the Angels of the Lord purſue and
chaſe them. Let the enemies of God and his people periſh: But let Chriſt
and his Saints live and Reigne for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, which is the deſires of him, who my
Lord, deſires your happineſſe and preſervation with the reſt of his
Saints, and deſires to be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours much obliged And moſt Humble Servant
<hi>F. L.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117498:2"/>
            <head>THE KINGDOMES DIVISIONS <hi>ANATOMYZED.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N Admiring, I cannot but Admire, at the divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence
of the Almighty, which hath cauſed ſuch ſtrange and wonderfull Mutations
and Alterations in this afflicted State and Kingdome; but ſurely, it is his
good pleaſure hereby, to declare his <hi>Works,</hi> his ſtrange
<hi>Works;</hi> and bring to paſſe his <hi>Acts.</hi> That ſo his
<hi>glorious footſteps might appeare, both in wayes of judgement and mercy to
his People.</hi> Pſalm. 101.1 <hi>&amp;</hi> 65.5.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>SIR,</hi> In the Spring of the yeare, conſidering of the
ſtrange and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent Commotions and Inſurrections that were in the
<hi>North</hi> and <hi>South,</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and
<hi>Weſterne</hi> parts of this Kingdome; I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, that a deluge of
miſery would attend the Saints; apprehending that the Powers of Earth and
Hell, would certainly be muſtered up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; <hi>But the Lord of
Hoſts hath appeared for us, and the God of Armies hath been our refuge,</hi>
Selah. <hi>And bleſſed for ever be Jehovah, who hath broken in peeces the
horne of their ſtrength; for wherein his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies have dealt proudly,
himſelfe hath been above them; It is he that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dues the enemies of his
people, and overturneth the Horſe and his Rider: And reproveth Princes,</hi>
(And why not <hi>Parliaments,</hi> if need be, or evill <hi>Members</hi>
therin) <hi>for the ſakes of his Saints.</hi> I remember, though di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
yeares ſince, An expreſſion of that exceeding Learned, Reverend, Holy,
and Faithfull Teacher, Mr. <hi>John Cotton</hi> of <hi>Boſton,</hi> in
<hi>New England,</hi> which was to this effect, <hi>viz.</hi> That God would
poure his wrath upon the Court of <hi>England.</hi> As alſo, That Seats of
Judicature would not <pb n="2" facs="tcp:117498:3"/> throw down <hi>Babylon.</hi> And I
beleeve, much leſſe would they alone ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt Chriſt, and his Churches. But
it muſt be done with violence, <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.21. And this day is his
ſaying, and this Scripture fulfilled in our eares: It is Propheſied
concerning Chriſt in his conqueſt, <hi>That he ſhall ſtricke through
Kings, in the day of his wrath.</hi> And I beleeve it is not <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi>
Soveraigne, whoſe Head ſhall alone be taken off and wounded; but the Heads
of many Countries, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 110.5.6. And truely, this honour have all
the Saints, <hi>To bind their Kings in chaines, and their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blos in fetters of
Iron.</hi> And not onely to paſſe Sentence, but to execute upon them the
Judgement written, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 149. from the 6. <hi>verſ.</hi> to the
laſt. And though, through the power and grace of the moſt High, Theſe
Scriptures have had their accompliſhments in precedent Ages, yet in our dayes
more eminently; and doubtleſſe will more and more in ſucceeding
generations.</p>
            <p>The great Queſtion at preſent amongſt Gods People, is,
whether the Propheſie concerning the ſlaying of the Witneſſes be
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready fully accompliſhed, according to the 11. of the <hi>Revel.</hi>
7.8,9, and 10. or whether it remaine ſtill to be fulfilled; which, I
confeſſe, is at preſent dubious; though, I beleeve, a few yeares more,
will put it out of doubt; and yet it looks, at preſent, as if it were the
time of the Saints prevailing, and ſo of the Churches deliverance, according
to the 11. <hi>v.</hi> of the ſame <hi>Chapter;</hi> its true, for this three
or foure yeares laſt paſt, I found that all ſorts of men, had, as it
were, prepared Appetites to ſwallow up the Saints. And, doubtleſſe, had
their power been accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their ſpirit, they would certainly have
devoured, and eaten them up like bread; But now there is an appearance, as if a
Spirit of life from God were entred into men. And great feare fallen upon them
that ſee it, and a great Earthquake in our civill State, and earthly Powers;
as alſo in the hearts of earthly men; and equivalent to the words of the
Text. There ſeemes to be a tenth, if not ten parts of this great City fallen,
I meane, in their ſpirits; how many ſhall be ſlaine, the Lord on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
knowes; doubtleſſe, there is a remnant affrighted, and I wiſh they would
give glory to God.</p>
            <p>Againe, I finde this to be very true, that the Nations, and
people, both <hi>Popiſh,</hi> and <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> are exceeding angry,
they fume, foame, and ſnuffe for anger. Some fretting their hearts, and
gnawing their tongues, for paine, and as if Hell were let looſe,
blaſpheming the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, being ſcorched with great heat, and filled
with paines and ſores, but <pb n="3" facs="tcp:117498:3"/> repent not of their deeds.
<hi>Revel.</hi> 11.18. <hi>the</hi> 16.10. <hi>and</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>Moreover, I finde the ſpirits of the beſt Saints much
refreſhed, and as it were, in ſome meaſure, through grace prepared, to
ſing <hi>Halleiujah,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Bleſſed be the Name of our God,
for the Kingdomes of this world, are become the Kingdomes of the Lord, and of
his Chriſt;</hi> the which I cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dially deſire, though my bloud, with
others, ſhould be ſacrificed for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> Taking a view of this perplexed and afflictted
Kingdom, I find in it as it were a threefold diviſion, or three kinds of men
paſſing under a threefold denomination, <hi>viz. Independent, Presbyterian,
Malignant.</hi> Though I doubt not but in Gods due time the purer ſort of
<hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> will turn <hi>Independant,</hi> as the rotten and
corrupt, if they durſt would turn <hi>Malignant,</hi> And indeed, I have as
much hope, if not more, of divers <hi>Malignants</hi> then of them.</p>
            <p>The firſt are <hi>Independants</hi> ſo called; the which if I
miſtake not, is a word of deriſion caſt upon the pureſt ſort of
profeſſors in the Kingdom. A people though ſmall and deſpiſed; yet
ſundry of them through grace highly and divinely principled, acting to high
and divine ends, fighting under Chriſts Banner, and maugre men and Devills;
do zealouſly and eminently appear for Chriſt and his Church: amongſt whom
I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conceive it were but requiſite to diſtinguiſh, <hi>viz.</hi>
betwixt ſuch as are truly godly, and tenderly conſcientious; though
differing from other godly and ſound men, in ſuch opinions as do neither
prejudice faith nor a ſanctified courſe, and betwixt ſuch as are groſly
opinionated, whoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions do neceſſarily lead them into groſſe
practices; who according to the apprehenſions of ſundry learned and godly
men, are by no meanes to be tolerated, as having in them too much of the ſeed
of the Serpent, and a ſerpentine deſgine, to undermine and overturn both
the faith of a Chriſtian, and the foundation of true conſtituted
Churches.</p>
            <p>The ſecond are <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> ſo nominated, many of
whom I eaſily believe to be very precious in Gods ſight, and ſuch whom I
dare not but both love and honour, howbeit I much feare there be too many which
paſſe under this denomination, who are too much inclined to malignan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy or
a connivance at it, as appeares by their extream unſeemly, and
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianly expreſſions. Some ſaying, they had rather be ſlaves
under the <hi>Turks;</hi> others, they had rather the <hi>King,</hi> with his
Army had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed, chuſing rather to be under the power of Popery and
Prelacy, then Independency, as they call it: as if they ſhould ſay, they
had rather <pb n="4" facs="tcp:117498:4"/> be under the power of the Devill and
Antichriſt, then under the power of Chriſt and his Saints; Theſe, and the
like, have my ſelf heard expreſt, and that by ſome who are deemed godly.
Beſides the extream uncivill, and not to be expreſt Language: they breath
forth againſt his Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy the Lord Gen. <hi>Fairfax,</hi> Lieutenant Gen.
<hi>Cromwell,</hi> Commiſſary Gen. <hi>Ireton,</hi> with others of the
gallant and godly Commanders of the Army amongſt the doggs, of whoſe flocks
they are ſcarcely to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted. Now theſe things, under favour, to me
argue high Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy; and ſuch things, which I dare ſay, ſome
Malignants, through their Morality and Civility, would abhorre to expreſſe.
Yet ſet me mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly expreſſe my ſelfe concerning theſe men; I
conceive them to be ſuch, as deſire ſome a kind of Government alſo;
though they chuſe not their Magiſtrates to be of the pureſt, nor their
Government the ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteſt; and therefore they ſtand at large for a King
and Parliament.</p>
            <p>But before I paſſe this kinde, let me crave libertie to
inſert a few words concerning them; I ſhould, under favour, conceive it but
meet, That theſe men ſhould be as little tollerated, as groſſe
<hi>Opinioniſts. Sir,</hi> my conſcience beares me witneſſe, that I
intend not in the leaſt, any god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and innocent man, though a
<hi>Preſbyterian;</hi> and I beleeve, which I hope, without offence, I may
ſpeake; <hi>viz.</hi> That neither your ſelfe, the Army, High Court of
Juſtice, or Parliament; would, or durſt touch any of Gods Annointed in this
kind; or lay the leaſt of your fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers upon the leaſt of the Saints as
Saints.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe, if any <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> or other, though
poſſibly, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe godly; whether any <hi>Member</hi> impeached, or
ſuch as have prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched; together with others amongſt them, who in their
Prayers, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Printings, Practiſes, private Diſcourſes, and
conſultations, ſhall behave themſelves, more like rayling
<hi>Rabſhachas,</hi> curſing <hi>Shemeis,</hi> ſchof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing
<hi>Iſhmaels,</hi> then ſweet and meek Chriſtians. I humbly conceive in
this caſe, they may be looked at, as obſtructors and interruptors of the
Kingdomes peace, both Civill and Eccleſiaſticall; and may ſo be
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded againſt, notwithſtanding their Devotion and Profeſſion. The
devout <hi>Jewes</hi> perſecuted and ſtirr'd up the Raskallity of the
people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Paul,</hi> as ſome now would gladly doe againſt
<hi>Peeters,</hi> ſetting all the City upon an uproare, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.5.
And it is very well known, the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi>
notwithſtanding their devotion and profeſſions, were Chriſts and his
Diſciples chiefeſt and greateſt enemies.</p>
            <p>There was a Booke lately Printed, ſubſcribed as I remember
with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <pb n="5" facs="tcp:117498:4"/> 47. <hi>Presbyterians</hi> hands; I ſeeing a
godly and diſcret Gentleman reading therein, deſired to know how he
approved of it? He anſwered, it was a Bull. Now I well remember, that many
years ſince I had heard of a popiſh Bull, but to live to ſee a
<hi>Presbyterian</hi> Bull, it could not but ſeem exceeding ſtrange to me,
as being ſuch a Beaſt as I think the world it ſelf never heard of untill
now; And truly to me, it adminiſters matter of ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and lamentation,
that learned and godly <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> ſhould act the parts of
ungodly and popiſh <hi>Prelats.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Object. 1. <hi>But they ſay, in ſo doing they diſcharge
their conſciences, and thinke they do God and their Countreymen good
ſervice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> So did <hi>Paul,</hi> whilſt being
<hi>Saul</hi> was little better then ſtarke ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring mad, in perſecuting
the Saints; and yet did nothing but what in conſcience, he then verily
thought he ought to have done. <hi>Acts</hi> 26.9.10.11. And I cordially
wiſh, they would be pleaſed ſeriouſly to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of it; for truly
it ſeemes to me, as if there were a viall of contempt from heaven powred upon
the ſpirit, that too frequently breaths from theſe men, though themſelves
may otherwiſe in the roote, be ſincere and godly.</p>
            <p>Alas their very Religion, I mean, of the
<hi>Presbyterianiſme,</hi> being a poore <hi>Scottiſh</hi> and humane
inſtitution, received but a humane grant for about three years; never
proſpered from the firſt and I doubt not, but it will be blaſted at the
laſt, and no marvell; for it is to be feared their <hi>Alpha</hi> and
<hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mega,</hi> was not <hi>Jehovah,</hi> but themſelves; and that which had
not its riſe and foundation, before all time, muſt needs in time
periſh.</p>
            <p>But take a true conſtituted <hi>Presbyter,</hi> and the God of
all grace for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, that either my ſelf, or any Profeſſing the fear of
God, ſhould have the leaſt ryſing of heart againſt it.</p>
            <p>I could with all my heart deſire that all the true
Congregational Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, both in City and Kingdom were not ſo defective in
this reſpect; but that they were more and more ſtudious and diligent, to
obtaine and eſtabliſh a full and compleate <hi>Presbytery,</hi> in all
their ſeverall Churches; that ſo all the Ordinances of Chriſt, might be
diſpenced with more Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and authority, and the members of Chriſt
that come from forragn parts the more refreſhed, whilſt they behold the
Churches of the Saints walking in the compleat Order of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Object. 2. <hi>But further, ſome ſay, that the Army, and I
beleive they meane this Parliament alſo be none of their parents, nor
themſelves their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:117498:5"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Then both Parliament and Army
hath leſſe to care for, and if they were not the more mercifull ſhould
caſt them out, both of their proviſion and protection; and proceed
againſt them as Rebells. The God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> reſpects, neither
accepts any man: as he is <hi>Scotch</hi> or <hi>Engliſh;</hi> but in his
ſonne, as he is a man fearing God, and working righteouſnes. <hi>Acts</hi>
10.34.35. Nor doth he reject any man, becauſe he is <hi>Spaniſh, Portugal,
Grecian</hi> or <hi>Ethiopian,</hi> but as he is an enemy to the life of God
and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.8. Now if <hi>Engliſh</hi> men be ſuch as
their ſpeech bewrayeth them, and agrees thereto, why then the fathers and
Judges of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> are to be like God.</p>
            <p>But what if it appear, that thoſe that are denyed, be proved to
be the parents of the Kingdom, and they their children, as I beleive it will;
For firſt, it hath been often prayed for, many times fought for, and twice
procured by conqueſt; and bleſſed be God for ſuch parents. And plaine
it is, though divers <hi>Presbyterians</hi> will not acknowledge it, that it
hath pleaſed God, to be-truſt the ſole power of the Kingdom in their
hands; and in whoſe hands, of ſuch gracious ſpirits, I deſire it might
for ever be preſerved; And if theſe children will not be warned, then may
the parents, both by the Law of God and nature, give them ſevere
chaſtiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ement and correction.</p>
            <p>Object. 3. <hi>But ſay they, the Army have broken down the
hedge, taken away godly Magiſtrates and left only ſuch men, as are of their
own minds and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, they have not broaken down the hedge,
but pluckt up the crooked and rotten ſtakes that ſo the hedge might ſtand
more even and firme.</p>
            <p>And if it ſhould be granted, that ſome of the impeached
members were godly, yet were they not impeached for their godlynes in the
leaſt; but wherin they were both ungodly and unrighteous. It's true,
Magiſtrates are called Gods, being ordained of God to act according to God;
And in ſo doing, are to be honoured and obeyed of all men. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.
from tee 1. to the 6. the 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 13 and 14. But wherein they act like
devills, they ceaſe to be Gods, and therein are not to be regarded.</p>
            <p>And wherein they ſay, <hi>the Armie have onely paſſed by
ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of their own
opinions,</hi> is as groſſe a miſtake as the other; For there are as
ſound and godly remaining in the houſe, and that <hi>Presbyterians</hi>
alſo if not farre better then any that were impeached; Nor did they in the
leaſt intend, either <hi>Presbyterian</hi> or <hi>Independent,</hi> as
ſuch; but as they were men <pb n="7" facs="tcp:117498:5"/> acting againſt the glory of
God, and the good of the Kingdom; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it plainly appeares, the
<hi>Presbyterian</hi> party were moſt to blame, being like the adverſaries
of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Benjamin,</hi> mentioned in the 4 of <hi>Ezra.</hi>
the 15. who in pretending to build, intended to undermine the very
foundation.</p>
            <p>Object. 4. <hi>But ſay they again, The Army acted out of their
Sphear?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, that alſo is a miſtake. Their
Commiſſions run full to ſubdue the Common enemy; and if I may ſpeak it
without offence, in caſe the whole Parliament had proved ſuch: as
bleſſed be God they have not, and I hope never will; but if they had, why a
Parliament ſhould be ſuffered to ruin a Kingdom more then a Prince, I know
no reaſon at all, eſpecially when God hath given a Kingdom, power to
prevent it.</p>
            <p>Moreover, this Army hath not onely been barely permitted, but in
an eſpeciall manner bleſſed by God; And whatſoever mens ends were in
rayſing of them, doubtleſſe Gods ends were, as to revenge the quarrell of
his Covenant and ſubdue his enemies: ſo to redeeme his own glory, and his
peoples liberties, and priviledges, out of the hands of their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors.
And thats the work that this Parliament and Army are to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, maugre men and
devills in the proſecution thereof.</p>
            <p>Obiect. 5. <hi>But they again ſay, that this Army uſeth
violence, but violence and the ſword will never rule this Kingdom?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, when God comes to overturn
<hi>Babylon,</hi> and to turne Nations topſie turvie, and upſide down; then
violence is uſed, not only by Gods bare permiſſion; but by his ſpeciall
ordination and inſtitution. <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.21. And how theſe great works
of God ſhould be done without violence, no man can imagine.</p>
            <p>And as for the ſword, it hath been of ancient and ſingular
uſe, both in Civills and Spiritualls, and that amongſt the beſt of
Saints, witnes <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Gen.</hi> 14.14.15.16. and <hi>Nehemiah, Neh.</hi>
the 4. from the 13. to the end. And the truth is, there is an abſolute
neceſſity of a ſword; for Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions would never yet be ruled without it:
And there are two ſwords eſpecially which hath govern'd the world,
<hi>viz.</hi> The ſword of Satan and Antichriſt: and the ſword of
Chriſt and his Saints. Now under the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the firſt ſword the
nations have lyen a long time; But under the power of the ſecond the Nations
cannot indure, though they muſt nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will nor chuſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Rev.</hi>
11.7. the 12.7. the 17.14. the 19. from the 13. to the end. Chriſt now hath
put the ſword into the hands of his Saints, and there he will preſerve and
maintaine it, till it be ſheath'd in <pb n="8" facs="tcp:117498:6"/> the bowells of
Antichriſt; I mean the harlot of <hi>Rome,</hi> that Beaſt together with
the falſe prophet the Pope, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20. And after him the
<hi>Turke</hi> alſo. And if it ſhould ſo fall out, that another ſtorme
ſhould fall upon Gods people, which the Lord prevent; yet theſe clouds
would ſuddenly be diſperſt, and then the ſword will certainly reſt in
the hands of Chriſt &amp; his Saints, untill all their enemies be ſubdued;
And to this ſword the Nations, will they, nill they, muſt both buckle and
bow.</p>
            <p>The Lord Jeſus will rule till his enemies be made his
foot-ſtoole, and for the Saints, let them rejoyce in him that made them; Let
the children of Sion be joyfull in their King. Let the high praiſes of God be
in their mouths, and a two edged ſword in their hands, to execute vengeance
upon the Heathen: and puniſhments upon the people. To bind their Kings with
chaines, and their Nobles with fetters of Iron. To execute upon them the
judgment written, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 149. This honour have all his Saints. And the
ſword of the Saints, is put together with the ſword of the Lord; as the
warres of the Saints is called the Lords warres. <hi>Num.</hi> 21.14.</p>
            <p>Object. 6. <hi>The Army did well whilſt they oppoſed Lyons,
Tygers, Wolves, &amp;c. but now they ſtrike, and catch at ſheep
alſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It's true, they did before oppoſe Wolves; but
they do not now ſtrike at ſheep: but at Wolves in Sheeps cloathing; a black
Devill is more ugley to look upon, but a white Devill is as deſtructive; when
Satan transformed himſelf into an Angell of light he prejudiced the ſoule
as much as as if he appeared in his own colours. <hi>Luke</hi> 16.27. to the
end.</p>
            <p>Object. 7. <hi>There are a godly and wiſe people both in
new</hi> England, <hi>and ſomtimes come hither; but they approve not of
theſe proceedings but are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies thereunto?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, the firſt part is true, but not the
latter, It's true there is here and there a Raven come over, who finding
garbiſh here to feed upon, though they have been thither called have not
returned; and it may well be, that thoſe have rather ſtrengthned the hands
of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Malignants and formall <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> then of the people
of God; But bleſſed be God there have been ſundry Doves come over, ſome
of whom have returned with Olive branches in their mouths: And others remaining
in Parliament, Army, City, and elſe where; who have Dove like behaved
themſelves, and have been of ſpeciall uſe ſince hither they came,
<hi>viz.</hi> Sir <hi>Henry <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aine,</hi> Mr. <hi>Phenix,</hi> Col.
<hi>Humphrey,</hi> Mr. <hi>Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> 
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:117498:6"/> Mr. <hi>Peters,</hi> Mr. <hi>Richard
Huchinſon, Janice. &amp;c.</hi> Whom I hope will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe me for mentioning
of them; And I doubt not, but by Gods grace and aſſiſtance, will prove
bleſſings to the Kingdom whiles here they remaine.</p>
            <p>And as for <hi>New-England</hi> it ſelf, though too many
Legaliſts amongſt them, yet to my knowledge there are divers, who
bleſſed be God are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding wiſe &amp; ſpirituall; and ſome of
theſe divers years ſince, have often prophecied of theſe times,
frequently and fervently prayed for them, and I doubt not but will bleſſe
God alſo when they heare of the ſuccesfull victories God hath given to his
people; all which plainly argues their harmony and congruity, and not their
diſapprovement and enmity.</p>
            <p>Nor will I affirme leaſt I ſhould miſtake, what I have heard
that emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently learned and pious teacher Mr. <hi>John Cotten</hi>
expreſſe; But this I remember, though divers years ſince, that as he
ſaid God would bring a ſword upon <hi>England,</hi> and certainly powre his
wrath upon the Court of <hi>England,</hi> which things are eminently come to
paſſe: So he likewiſe hath prophecied of a ſword that would fall upon
<hi>Scotland,</hi> I pray God the miniſters of that Kingdom would be no
cauſe of it; And though I judge not Mr. <hi>Cotten</hi> to be infallable, yet
in my obſervation things have gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſucceeded according to the
Counſell of God declared by him. And its much deſired, did the honourable
Parliament ſee it ſo good, he might be ſent for, it would be looked at,
both by <hi>Presbyterian</hi> and <hi>Independent,</hi> as an extraordinary
advantage and bleſſing to the Kingdom. But what if all <hi>New-England</hi>
wanted light, to ſee into the equity and neceſſity of their proceedings,
doth that upon neceſſity argue the illegality there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? they are not only
to walk up to the light of <hi>New-England,</hi> (though that light doth as
farre exceed the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> light in <hi>Scotland,</hi> as theirs
doth the Popiſh) but to the light of the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which is
accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the word of God, and the firſt Article of the Covenant.</p>
            <p>Object. 8. <hi>The great and grand objection is, That this
Parliament and Army, is for a Tolleration and Liberty of Conſcience, and that
will undoe all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, firſt by the way, there be three
things which ſundry eminent Chriſtians, could never to this day well
digeſt, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfull word <hi>Independent,</hi>
caſt upon the pureſt Saints, The truth is they are dependant, depending
upon the Lord Jeſus for all their Lawes, Ordinances, Statutes, and
Inſtitutions. And whilſt they walk according to God therein, they are a
Non-ſuch in the world; and the <hi>Scotch</hi> ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, <pb n="10" facs="tcp:117498:7"/>
or any other in this caſe, had better eate fire
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>The Second is the Covenant, which was ever feared, would proves
ſhare to the Saints and Kingdom.</p>
            <p>The third is a tolleration, and Liberty of Conſcience, which I
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their
affinity.</p>
            <p>Now for to deſire a Tolleration of any thing that is corrupt,
whether in opinion, or practice: ſeemes under favour, to be but a corrupt
deſire; And to deſire a Tolleration of the Truth, or of Gods pure
Worſhip<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſeems to reflect diſhonour upon Chriſt; For the Truth
ſhould be prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed, and God purely worſhiped, in deſpight of all
gain-ſayers and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers, whether men or Divells. I hope I need not
deſire my boldneſſe to be excuſed, it is for Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And as for Liberty of Conſcience, the tearm it ſelf ſeems
not to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the pattern of wholſome words; but if it may
paſſe, then may it admit of a double conſtruction. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Liberty of Conſcience to ſinne, which implyes rather
a captivity then Liberty, for men to profeſſe and practice what they
liſt. If this be deſired, and granted: it is that which God, and all that
are born of him, abhort, and this indeed would undo all. But their is a Liberty
of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in pure worſhiping of God, and keeping cloſe to his Lawes
and Truth; and the more ſtrictly the conſcience is bound in this caſe,
the more by far is it's liberty and inlargment, <hi>Iames</hi> 1.25. And this
is the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty that I hope, and am confident the Parliament and divers of the
Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſtands for, that ſo the godly and unimbittered <hi>Presbyterian,</hi>
with the ſincere and ſound hearted <hi>Independant,</hi> might purely
Worſhip and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> with their God,
without perſecution or moleſtation; and this Liberty will not undo and
deſtroy, but reſtore and preſerve all. Ah when will theſe dayes be!
Haſten the time O God, wherein the holy people of God howſoever called or
diſtinguiſhed, may unanimouſly meete to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſweetly and
harmoniouſly to imbrace each other.</p>
            <p>Object. 9. <hi>Their be ſundry other Objections which ſcarce
deſerve the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning,</hi> viz. <hi>That the Army hath many wicked men,
ſundry Jeſuits, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> their
astions aime at themſelves?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That there are too many wicked men in the Army I
feare is too true, and were it poſſible, I could wiſh there were none;
but that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> is ſaid to be ſo
many Jeſuits, I beleive it not; but if both be true, it doth no more argue
the Armies diſhoneſty and illegallity, then the being of ſtone in a
Chriſtian mans heart, argues his non-ſincerity; and are as
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:117498:7"/> tollerated
by the godly Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y in the Army; as
Drunkards and Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers are in <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Congregations; and as
for their aiming at themſelves in their Actions, I Anſwer, Firſt, their
Actions face to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a generall good, and we are not to become Judgers of
evill thoughts; nor to receive evil Jealouſies where there is contrary
appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances; but it rather argues too much ſelfe, and iniquity in our
ſelves, that we would not have theſe who are Inſtruments of a common and
generall good, ſo much as to have any ſhare therein, who indeed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
the beſt; and whoſe particular good, muſt upon neceſſity be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved
in the generall.</p>
            <p>Now then, I doe by no meanes beleeve its lawfull to raiſe a new
War; or riſe in Rebellion againſt this Parliament and Army, Though ſome
<hi>Presbyterians</hi> Prayers, Preachings, Printings, practiſes, tend
thereto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ſword hath already divided betwixt the
Independent and Malignant, and if I know my heart could freely ſacrifice my
life, it might proceed no further: But if it muſt likewiſe divide betwixt
the Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an and Independent, the good will of God be done. As I have but
one life, had I ten times ten thouſand, and as many ſoules, by the help of
Chriſt I ſhould freely adventure them all in the Cauſe; as being
confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent the Independent in his Cauſe, will firſt or laſt prevaile,
(and never fall more;) for I find in the ſounding of the ſeventh Angel,
that there were great voyces in Heaven, ſaying, the Kingdoms of this world
are become the Kingdoms of the Lord, and of his Chriſt, and he ſhall reigne
for ever and ever, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. which is likely to have part of its
accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment in the next prevailing Independent Battle, if not before:
which I looke at, as the battles which were fought in Heaven, by
<hi>Micha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> and his Angels, with the Dragon and his; but the latter
prevailed not, neither was their place found any more. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.7,8.
But this Warre ends not till the Church of <hi>Roome,</hi> the beaſt, with
the falſe Prophet, the Pope: together, with their Confederates, be taken and
ſlaine. <hi>Revel.</hi> 19. from 13. to the end.</p>
            <p>Nevertheles, <hi>Sir,</hi> for as much as it is not improbable,
but that freſh Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults and Inſurrections may againe break forth. Let me
humbly &amp; ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly requeſt you to ſtirre up both Parl. and Army to
uſe all good meanes to prevent, a Serpent is with more facility cruſht in
the ſhell, then after breaking forth; witneſs <hi>Kent, Colcheſter,</hi>
&amp; the <hi>Scots;</hi> together with which furious Malignant, was ſubtilty
and ſecretly involved; A moſt dangerous and fiery <hi>Presbyterian</hi>
Serpent; And Serpents in <hi>May</hi> 
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:117498:8"/> will begin to looke
forth. <hi>Sir,</hi> I queſtion not your wiſdomes in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>g with theſe, I neither doe, nor dare preſcribe a
way themſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> concerning
<hi>Independants</hi> or <hi>Opinioniſts,</hi> as they call them, would
gladly have had the Parliament to have writ after <hi>New Englands</hi> Copy;
which if they ſhould, then would theſe men be baniſh'd the Kingdome, for
there was Mr. <hi>Wheelewright,</hi> A man approved for piety, integrity,
inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, and humulity, and yet baniſh'd <hi>New England,</hi> being farre
leſſe guilty then theſe men, if at all; which in conſcience, I neither
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, nor would have mentioned,
ſave that it is ſo well known; and I hope, they would not doe the like
againe: And though I have many things to commend <hi>New England</hi> for, as
apprehending them to be the beſt go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd people, and to have the beſt
government both of Civill and Church State, that to my knowledge is extant in
the world; yet in this I commend them not, for truth ſhould not ſuffer with
error and falſehood, nor the innocent with the guilty: which things I humbly
referre to the honourable Magiſtrats wiſdome, and diſcretion.</p>
            <p>The third, and laſt ſort, are Malignants, ſo called, divers
of whom, I doubt not, have been Civilly and Morrally educated; and ſundry of
whom it is to be hoped, may pertaine to the election of grace.</p>
            <p>Yet if without offence, I may expreſſe my ſelfe concerning
ſome of this kind; which I deſire to doe with compaſſion, as alſo
with a deſire of their Converſion, if God ſo pleaſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Then I much
feare that too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of this kind may be ſtrongly ſuſpected, to be the
very ſonnes of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liall,</hi> and of <hi>Abaddonitiſh</hi> and
deſtructive Spirits, directly oppoſite to both the other; eſpecially, to
the firſt mentioned, that inſtead of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing divinely, are diabolically
principled: acting to their own ends, and lights; And inſtead of fighting
under Chriſts banner, and appearing for Chriſt, and his Church, doe
directly fight under the Banner of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, and plainely ſtand up for the
Devill and Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>There are three things which diſturbe the Earth, yea foure, why
it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be quiet; <hi>viz.</hi> The ſuperſtitious and Idolatrous
<hi>Bapiſt,</hi> The groſſe and profane <hi>Malignant,</hi> The carnall
and formall <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> And the blaſphemious <hi>Heretique.
SIR,</hi> its not improbable, but that I ſhall paſſe under many
Cenſures, for what I have here expreſt, but I bleſſe God, I weigh not
mans day; as having borne witneſſe to the truth, and againſt the
contrary; and that without prejudice or partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie to any as in Gods
ſight.</p>
            <p>Now from the Generation of ſuperſtitious Papiſts, and
prophane Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants, <pb n="13" facs="tcp:117498:8"/> of fiery Presbyterians, and
blaſphemous <hi>Hereticks.</hi> The Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver <hi>Zion,</hi> as I believe
he will; and will alſo daſh in peeces all earthly Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs &amp; powers,
that do oppoſe himſelf and Saints; And in his due time, will doubtleſs
reign throughout the Kingdoms of the world. I mean not perſonally, for I by
no meanes apprehend that, though I highly honour ſome that are thought ſo
to conceive; but powerfully and ſpiritually in the hearts and lives of his
Saints, from one Generation to another, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4.6. Againſt whom,
if your ſelf, the Army, or Parliament ſhould act, againſt whom you would
implicitly act; if you ſhould not as much as in you lies, go through with
that good and glorious work which the Lord hath now betruſted you with; yea,
doubtleſſe, though it be againſt nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall Lawes, having a word of God
to bear you out, <hi>Eſther</hi> 4.16. 2 of <hi>Kings</hi> 14.19. yea though
you carry it all along by violence, <hi>Ezra</hi> 4.3. 5.2. <hi>Nehe.</hi>
4.13.14. againſt whom I ſay, if you ſhould act, then doubtleſſe would
the God of <hi>Izrael</hi> blaſt you, and your proceedings; But on the
contrary, notwithſtanding the uncharitable thoughts, jealouſies, and
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions; which others have of you, in caſe you act: As verily, I
hope, through grace many of you do. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the glory of Chriſt, the proſperity of Zion, and publicke
Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, in which doing, you expreſſe your faithfulneſſe to God,
to the Saints, to the Kingdomes, and alſo to the Covenant. And cauſe the
Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Shuſhan</hi> to rejoyce and be glad, <hi>Ester</hi> 8.15. In
which doing, you will aſſuredly finde a bleſſing from the father of
bleſſings; and give the Generations to come cauſe alſo to call you
bleſſed; which is the deſire of him, who with Saints in ſincerity,
bleſſes God for yours, the Armies, and Parliaments preſent activitie; And
deſires to be in reallity, a Servant to the Lord, and his People.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>F. L.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Februarie</hi> 21.
1648-49</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Theodore Jennings.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
